<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2018-12-27T15:43:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4000//</id>

  
    <title type="html">Mike Brinker</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle>
  

  
    <author>
        <name>Mike Brinker</name>
      
      
    </author>
  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">How does DNS work?</title>
      
      
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/27/dns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does DNS work?" />
      
      <published>2018-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/27/dns</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/27/dns/">&lt;p&gt;Whether you realize it or not, DNS is a workhorse of the internet ecosystem. It provides the glue that allows someone like your grandma, (who knows that you want a pair of Adidas Ultraboost from footlocker.com for Christmas) to talk TCP with a server on the other side of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing when you think about it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your grandma really is quite kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s start from first principles and dig in to understand DNS a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-dns&quot;&gt;What exactly is DNS?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DNS, or the &lt;em&gt;Domain Name System&lt;/em&gt; is an abstraction layer that maps the human-readable web addresses that we know and love to IP addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, that was about the extent of my knowledge of DNS. I knew that there were servers out in the ether of the internet that contained those mappings.  Later on, I learned that one could use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nslookup&lt;/code&gt; to find existing mappings. Beyond that, I knew very little. The majority of the time this was enough, but every now and then I would hear someone mention an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; record or a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; record and I couldn’t contribute much to the conversation other than “Ah yes, that has something to do with DNS”.  If you are like me, the things that you know that you don’t know server as bread crumbs for the things that you want to learn.  Let’s follow those breadcrumbs a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lifecycle-of-a-dns-query&quot;&gt;The lifecycle of a DNS query&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interview questions like “Tell me everything that happens when I navigate to google.com” are quite fun to answer for me.  This is mainly because there are endless ways to tell the story of all the things that go on when a user does x.  At some point though, we have to limit the detail of our explanations in order to actually provide value. Be forewarned: the explanatory lifecycle of a DNS query below is not exhaustive! Exhaustive references can be useful but not so much in didactic contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happens when a domain name query is issued to DNS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone named Jeffrey asks their computer to go to google.com&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The operating system of Jeffrey’s computer consults its own cache to see if the IP address for the requested name is already known. If it is, life is good! If not…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jeffrey’s operating system reaches out to a DNS cacher/recursor which we will refer to as the &lt;em&gt;local DNS server&lt;/em&gt; from here onward. The local DNS server is very often provided by your ISP, but sufficiently advanced LANs will often have their own local DNS server.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;local DNS server&lt;/em&gt; will check its cache. If it has an answer to the query, life is good! If not…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The local DNS server will recursively contact other DNS servers until it can provide an authoritative answer.  The recursive DNS request looks something like:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;local DNS server asks a root DNS server where to find the .com TLD (top level domain) server. The root DNS server provides the answer.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;local DNS server then asks the .com TLD DNS server for the “google” name server. The “google” name server provides an answer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the local DNS server returns the IP address provided by the “google” name server to Jeffrey’s computer. (and hopefully caches the answer!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-dns-record&quot;&gt;What is a DNS record?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The response provided by a DNS server represents a &lt;em&gt;record&lt;/em&gt; that exists in the Domain Name System. One might find that the responses representing records are referred to as a &lt;em&gt;record&lt;/em&gt; themselves. YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I explain a few of the common DNS record types. There are many more. For more details you may want to consult this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_DNS_record_types&quot;&gt;helpful and complete list&lt;/a&gt; of DNS record types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cname-records&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; Records&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; record is said to be “the canonical name for an alias” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035&quot;&gt;RFC 1035&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; records map an alias to another name. Upon receiving a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; response, the  computer issuing a DNS query will restart the query using the value that the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; record points too. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; records are intended to point to a canonical name, but there is nothing that prevents one from creating a CNAME record that point to another alias. One could even create an infinite loop if they so desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dname-records&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DNAME&lt;/code&gt; Records&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DNAME&lt;/code&gt; record “provides redirection for a subtree of the domain” accord to its RFC (&lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6672&quot;&gt;RFC 6672&lt;/a&gt;). For this reason is it known as a &lt;em&gt;delegation&lt;/em&gt; record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a--records&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;  Records&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; records are described as providing “a host address” in &lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1035&quot;&gt;RFC 1035&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; records are the meat and potatoes(?) of DNS. The provide a simple mapping from a name to an IP address.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="how things work" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">Whether you realize it or not, DNS is a workhorse of the internet ecosystem. It provides the glue that allows someone like your grandma, (who knows that you want a pair of Adidas Ultraboost from footlocker.com for Christmas) to talk TCP with a server on the other side of the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Weekly Reading List</title>
      
      
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/14/reading-list/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weekly Reading List" />
      
      <published>2018-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/14/reading-list</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/14/reading-list/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://robertheaton.com/2014/07/21/how-to-win-friends-and-influence-repos/&quot;&gt;How to win friends and influence repos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://michaelfeathers.silvrback.com/testing-yourself&quot;&gt;Testing Yourself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-read-of-the-week&quot;&gt;Best Read of the Week&lt;/h2&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="What I've Been Reading" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">How to win friends and influence repos Testing Yourself</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">The Bad Plus</title>
      
      
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/08/bad-plus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bad Plus" />
      
      <published>2018-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/08/bad-plus</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/08/bad-plus/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve found over the years that there is some music that is well-suited for listening while doing software-development related work and some music is not. Rather than try to derive a special formula for “coding music” I’m going to tell you about some music that works for me. One group I’ve been listening to for awhile that works particularly well is &lt;em&gt;The Bad Plus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bad Plus&lt;/em&gt; is a jazz piano trio that might not sound like a jazz group to you at first blush. They employ jazz idioms and instrumentation on popular cover tunes and their own originals as well. I find a wide range of mood and tone in their music: calm and nearly ambient, cacophonic excitement, and even straight ahead tunes with lots of energy. Despite the diversity it all works nicely when I’m clacking away on the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend catching them live if they are ever playing in your town. The occasions I’m which I had the priviledge of hearing The Bad Plus did not disappoint – YouTube has a nice selection of live recordings available. One can only hope they release more live music in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;song-selection-for-work&quot;&gt;Song Selection for Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anthem for the Earnest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flim&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As the Moment Slips Away&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beauty Has It Hard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are the Champions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prehensile Dream&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Silence is the Question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1983 Regional All-Star&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cQNybpWVS3o&quot;&gt;Newport Jazz Festival, 2006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=11YQwpNM1ng&quot;&gt;Moers Festival, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="Music I Listen To While Working" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve found over the years that there is some music that is well-suited for listening while doing software-development related work and some music is not. Rather than try to derive a special formula for “coding music” I’m going to tell you about some music that works for me. One group I’ve been listening to for awhile that works particularly well is The Bad Plus.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Weekly Reading List</title>
      
      
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/07/reading-list/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Weekly Reading List" />
      
      <published>2018-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2018-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/07/reading-list</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/07/reading-list/">&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cameronlonsdale.com/2018/11/26/whats-in-a-docker-image/&quot;&gt;What’s in a docker image?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://andresalmiray.com/the-gradle-pom/&quot;&gt;The gradle POM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoq.com/articles/serverless-sea-change&quot;&gt;Serverless Sea Change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Scientists find gut bacteria in the brain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1712.07962&quot;&gt;Dark matter solved and explained&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-read-of-the-week&quot;&gt;Best Read of the Week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The award goes to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infoq.com/articles/serverless-sea-change&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Serverless Sea Change&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
I’ve generally remained skeptical as to whether the advantages of serverless architectures outweight the benefits.
I remail skeptical, but this article does a great job of explaining and arguing for the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="What I've Been Reading" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">What’s in a docker image? The gradle POM Serverless Sea Change Scientists find gut bacteria in the brain Dark matter solved and explained</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
